"use strict";(self.webpackChunkclient=self.webpackChunkclient||[]).push([[923],{9923:function(e,t,a){a.r(t),a.d(t,{default:function(){return N}});var o=a(2791),r=a(4270),n=a(1327),i=a(9439),s=a(6582),l=a(824),h=a(9589),u=a(548),d=a(1660),y=a(1917),c=a(7280),m=a(5144),g=a(4735),p=a(2706),f=a(884),w=[{question:"How much can I afford to pay for a home?",answer:"To get an idea of how much you can afford, you'll need to know your taxable income, along with any outstanding debts and monthly payments.\n      First, calculate 39% of your income for use toward a mortgage payment, property taxes, and heating costs. If applicable, include half of estimated monthly condominium maintenance fees.\n      Next, make a second calculation, this time 44% of your taxable income. Then deduct all of your monthly debt payments, including car loans, credit cards, and line of credit payments.\n      The lesser of the first or second calculation will be used to help determine how much of your income may be used towards housing-related payments, including your mortgage payment. These calculations are based on lenders' usual guidelines.\n      In addition to considering what the ratios say you can afford, we'll help you determine exactly how much debt you/re comfortable servicing. If that amount is less than 39% of your income, you may want to settle for the lower amount rather than stretch yourself financially. Make sure you don't leave yourself 'house poor,' with not enough funds to spend on other things, like vacations. Structure your payments so that you can still afford simple luxuries. You'll also need to qualify for your mortgage amount, with new stress-test regulations released by the federal government.\n      Use our handy [Mortgage Affordability Calculator](INSERT LINK) for help with your numbers."},{question:"What is a home inspection and should I have one done?",answer:"In a word, yes. A home inspection is a visual examination of the property to determine the overall condition of the home. It should be done by a professional home inspector.\n      In this process, the inspector should be checking all major components, such as the roof, ceilings, walls, floors, foundations, crawl spaces, attics, and retaining walls. And all systems, such as electrical, heating, plumbing, drainage, and exterior weatherproofing. The results of the home inspection should be provided to the purchaser in written form, in detail, generally within 24 hours of the inspection.\n      A pre-purchase home inspection helps to protect your interests in an impending property investment by uncovering minor or significant issues (including major structural repairs) that may factor into your decision.\n      It can also add peace of mind to your choice and help you plan ahead for any repairs or maintenance that may be needed. A home inspection helps remove a number of unknowns and increases the likelihood of your successful purchase."},{question:"What is the minimum down payment needed to purchase a home?",answer:"A minimum down payment of 5% is required to purchase a home, subject to certain maximum price restrictions. Other situations, such as being self-employed or having poor credit, may also impact the required down payment amount.\n      In addition to the down payment, you must also be able to show that you can cover any applicable closing costs, such as legal fees, disbursements, appraisal fees (at True North Mortgage, we cover most appraisal fees), and a survey certificate, where applicable.\n      Regardless of the amount of the down payment, at least 5% of it must be from your own cash resources, or it can be in the form of a gift from a family member. For non-residents and newcomers to Canada, that amount typically rises to 10%, and cannot be borrowed.\n      Lenders will generally accept a gift from a family member as an acceptable down payment. In this case, the donor will need to provide a signed letter stating that it's a true gift, not a loan.\n      Mortgages with less than 20% down must have mortgage loan insurance provided by either [CMHC](INSERT CMHC LINK), [Sagen](INSERT SAGEN LINK), or [Canada Guaranty](INSERT CANADA GUARANTY LINK)."},{question:"What is mortgage loan insurance?",answer:"Mortgage loan insurance is legally required on mortgages with a Loan-to-Value (LTV) ratio greater than 80% (often called a high-ratio mortgage). It protects lenders against the risk of mortgage default and foreclosure by the borrower.\n      Usually paid by the borrower, the premiums for default insurance range from 0.50% to 7.0%. They can be added directly onto the mortgage amount or paid as a lump sum before the mortgage is advanced. This type of insurance is not the same as mortgage life insurance.\n      In Canada, mortgage default insurance is provided by three companies: [Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation (CMHC)](INSERT CMHC LINK), [Sagen](INSERT SAGEN LINK), and [Canada Guaranty](INSERT CANADA GUARANTY LINK). CMHC is a Crown corporation, while the other two are approved private corporations."},{question:"What is a conventional mortgage?",answer:"A conventional mortgage is usually one where the down payment is equal to 20% or more of the purchase price, with a Loan-to-Value (LTV) of 80% or less. It typically does not require mortgage default insurance, and so the borrower does not have to pay these insurance premiums. Mortgage interest rates may be slightly higher, however, for lenders to offset the lack of default insurance.\n        Read More: [Why a Bigger Down Payment Can Result in a Higher Rate](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"How does bankruptcy affect qualification for a mortgage?",answer:"After bankruptcy, it can be a challenge to re-establish your credit in securing a funded mortgage. However, depending on the circumstances surrounding your bankruptcy, some lenders may consider providing mortgage financing. Contact one of our friendly, expert brokers for more details.\n        Read More: [How Bankruptcy Can Affect a New Mortgage](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"How will child support affect your mortgage qualification?",answer:"For child support and alimony paid by you to another person, this amount is typically deducted from your total income before determining the size of mortgage you can qualify for.\n        If child support and alimony are received by you from another person, the amount is typically added to your total income before determining the size of mortgage you can qualify for \u2014 provided proof of regular receipt is available for a period of time determined by the lender."},{question:"Can I get a mortgage to purchase a home?",answer:"Yes, subject to qualification. With current historically-low rates, even purchasers with 5% down may qualify to buy a home and make improvements to it ([get pre-qualified here](INSERT LINK)). Any down payment under 20% will need mortgage default insurance obtained through CMHC, Sagen or Canada Guaranty.\n        If you're a first-time home buyer, there are government programs and incentives to help you get into the real estate market.\n        If you already own your home and want to purchase your next one to live in, you'll have a few more details to think about this time around (we can help with that, of course).\n        If you're buying a home that needs renovations right off the start, a Purchase Plus Improvements mortgage can include these upgrade costs along with the home price (some conditions will apply). This option eliminates the need to finance the home and renovations separately."},{question:"Can I use gift funds as a down payment?",answer:"Most lenders will accept down payment funds that are a gift from family. A gift letter signed by the donor is usually required to confirm that the funds are a true gift and not a loan. If mortgage default insurance is needed (with a down payment less than 20%), the lender or insurance provider may require the gift money to be in the purchaser's possession before the application is sent to them for approval."},{question:"What is a pre-approved mortgage?",answer:"A pre-approved mortgage is a solid idea of the maximum amount of mortgage that you qualify for, along with an interest rate guarantee from a lender for a specified period of time (usually 60 to 120 days). It's usually one of the first steps a home buyer should take when looking for a home or property.\n        A pre-approval does not absolutely guarantee that you'll receive the funds (as the final amount may be subject to conditions), but it's a very good indicator of the maximum amount you should consider when looking to purchase.\n        Your pre-approval process requires that you provide financial and credit score information in order to determine what size of loan you're eligible for, based on lender and government requirements and regulations. And, your down payment will be factored into the amount.\n        Most realtors prefer that you have a pre-approved mortgage in place before they take you out looking for a home or property. That way, they know they're showing you the right properties within your affordable price range.\n        Read More: [Pre-Qualify for a Mortgage in Minutes](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"How early can I renew my mortgage?",answer:"You can start your mortgage renewal process as early as 120 days (4 months) before the end of your current term, even if you haven't yet received your renewal offer. Lenders are only legally required to send your renewal statement at least 21 days before the deadline. Starting earlier provides more time to negotiate or look around for a better rate or mortgage fit.\n        Whether you've received your lender's renewal offer or ask them for it, it may come with a rate guarantee that covers the time frame left before your deadline. If rates happen to drop before the actual maturity date, the lender may also adjust your interest-rate offer lower.\n        The renewal rates first offered by your lender are often not the best ones you can get. They're typically based on posted rates with a 'discount' to help you feel that you're getting a deal. So, take this time to check out the possibility of getting a lower interest rate, either with your current lender or another one. You may find a better offer that will help you save money over your next term.\n        Don't sign without talking to us \u2014 we can do all the research and outline the process for you, and you'll have peace-of-mind that you're getting the best rate and mortgage fit for your situation.\n        Want a renewal reminder?"},{question:"What is a down payment?",answer:"Very few Canadian homebuyers have the cash available to buy a property outright. Most of us will turn to a financial institution for a mortgage, which can be the first step in a potentially long-standing mortgage relationship. But even with a mortgage, you'll first need to raise money for a down payment.\n        A down payment is the portion of the purchase price that you provide, which secures at least a small amount of equity in your home or property. It also indicates your financial commitment towards such a large purchase and resulting mortgage loan. The amount of your down payment should be determined well before you start house hunting or before getting a pre-approval.\n        The larger the down payment you can provide, the less your home or property will cost in the long run. A smaller mortgage also means the potential for lower interest and insurance costs, which can add up to significant savings over the life of your loan."},{question:"Can I buy a home with as little as 5% down?",answer:"Yes, it's possible to buy a home or property in Canada with a minimum of 5% down (subject to maximum price restrictions). Lenders are now able to offer this type of mortgage funding thanks to mortgage loan (default) insurance.\n        This default insurance is legally required on any mortgage with a down payment of less than 20% of the property price (called a high-ratio mortgage) and protects the lender from borrower default or foreclosure.\n        The premiums for mortgage loan insurance are usually paid by the borrower as a one-lump sum or are factored into the monthly mortgage payments. Borrowers are still responsible for all other associated fees, such as application, appraisal, and legal costs.\n        If you're a first-time home buyer, there are also government programs and incentives to help you get into the real estate market.\n        Read More: [First-Time Home Buyer Incentive Program](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"How can you pay off your mortgage faster?",answer:"Paying off your mortgage faster means you could save significant money on interest costs. Plus, you'll increase the equity in your home or property at a faster pace, as you pay down more principal. It's important to have the right mortgage product right off the start so that you have the flexibility you need to achieve your financial goals.\n        Depending on the lender and flexibility of your current mortgage, to pay off your mortgage faster, you can:\n        - Switch from a monthly to a biweekly accelerated payment schedule, which increases your payments to put more down on the principal.\n        - Make principal lump sum payments annually, or more often if the lender allows.\n        - Double-up your monthly payment.\n        - Select a shorter amortization when you renew your mortgage term.\n        Read More: [Pre-Payment Penalties and Privileges](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"How can I use RRSPs to help buy my first home?",answer:"If you're a first-time home buyer, the federal government has programs to help, including the Home Buyers' Plan (HBP). This program allows you to withdraw up to $35,000 in RRSP savings ($70,000 for a couple) to help finance your first down payment and to repay the withdrawn funds within a 15-year period.\n        Do you already have money saved for your first down payment? It may make good financial sense to apply your down payment through the Home Buyers' Plan \u2014 provided you have enough RRSP contribution room for the intended amount. You may receive a tax deduction that could be applied back to repaying the RRSP withdrawal amount or put towards other home expenses.\n        Our friendly, expert brokers can help you through all the details for this program and others offered by the government. As well, you can talk to your financial advisor about the benefits and considerations of the HBP. In addition to down payment info, we can help you save more with your best rate and mortgage fit.\n        Read More: [First-Time Home Buyer Incentive](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"What are the costs associated with buying a home?",answer:"There are several costs that you'll be responsible for when buying a home or property. Here's a quick list for reference:\n        - Down payment. You'll need to have at least 5% down, maybe more, depending on your situation. To qualify for a conventional mortgage, you will need a down payment of 20% or more.\n        - Deposit that counts towards your down payment, that is required by the seller to show your commitment to buy their property.\n        - Home inspection fee. We highly recommend a professional home inspection, which will bring to light areas of repair or maintenance and to ensure the house is structurally sound. Ask for a written report for your future reference.\n        - Mortgage default insurance (including PST) if you are putting less than 20% down. These premiums can be paid in a lump sum at the beginning or factored into your mortgage payments.\n        - Land Transfer Tax (LTT). Calculated as a percentage of the purchase price of the property, with the amount varying depending on the province.\n        - Legal fees, disbursements, and title insurance. These are costs that are associated with or are obtained through your solicitor. Fees for these services may vary significantly.\n        - Other closing costs, such as property insurance, tax or utility adjustments.\n        - Moving costs. Don't forget to include the cost of moving your belongings or paying for cleaning or upgrading before you officially move in.\n        \n        For an easy, complete breakdown of what costs apply to your particular situation, please contact one of our True North Mortgage specialists. They'll walk you through what you need to consider while getting your best rate and mortgage solution \u2014 from a lender that fits you. They also have trusted relationships for mortgage-related help if you need any referrals."},{question:"What should the length of my mortgage term be?",answer:"The length of a mortgage term can vary from six months up to 10 years. The term you choose will depend on your current financial situation, your short and long-term goals, your tolerance for risk, and even a choice between a variable vs. fixed rate.\n        \n        The majority of homeowners opt for a 5-year term to settle in with a particular rate (hopefully the best one you can get), especially if rates are lower. A shorter-term mortgage (1 to 3 years) may appeal to those who want to go with a variable rate for more savings (with a higher risk if rates go up), or if they think they may move again soon.\n        \n        In deciding on which term is best for you, here are some questions to consider:\n        - Do you plan to sell your house in the short-term without buying another? If so, a shorter mortgage term (6 months to 3 years) may be the best option.\n        - Do you believe that interest rates have bottomed out and are not likely to drop more? Then a longer mortgage term (4-10 years) may be the right choice for you.\n        - Similarly, if you think rates are currently high, you may want to opt for a short to medium length mortgage term, with the hope that rates drop by the time your term expires.\n        - Are you looking for security as a first-time home buyer? Then you may prefer a longer mortgage term, so that you can budget for and manage your monthly expenses.\n        - To save some money, are you willing to follow interest rates closely and risk having increased mortgage payments following a renewal? Then a shorter mortgage term will provide you with the ability to reduce your period of higher risk.\n        "},{question:"What are the monthly costs of owning a home?",answer:"Owning your own home can be a very rewarding personal and financial venture. But, it also comes with ongoing expenses, including maintenance and upgrade costs. Preparing ahead and continually budgeting will help you plan and pay for them as they come up.\n        \n        Here's a list of some costs associated with owning a home:\n        - Your Mortgage Payment: For many home buyers, this is the largest monthly expense. The actual amount of your mortgage payment can vary widely and is based on a number of variables, including your payment schedule, mortgage term, and amortization.\n        - Property Taxes: Property taxes are charged by the municipality you live in and are collected to pay for many civic services provided, such as garbage and recycling collection, snow removal and road maintenance, and policing and fire protection.\n        - School Taxes: In some municipalities, these taxes are integrated into property taxes. In others, they are collected separately and are payable in a single lump sum, usually due at the end of the current school year.\n        - Utilities: As a homeowner, you'll be responsible for all utility bills, including heating, gas, electricity, water, telephone, and cable.\n        - Maintenance and Upkeep: Owning a house comes with the cost of painting, roof repairs, electrical and plumbing, walks and driveway, lawn and tree care, and snow removal. A well-maintained property helps to preserve your home's market value. It also enhances the neighborhood, and depending on the kind of renovations you make, could even add further value to your property.\n        \n        Should I go with a short or long-term mortgage?\n        A longer-term mortgage is worth considering if you have a busy life and don't have time to watch mortgage rates. Our 4, 5, 7, and 10-year mortgages help you take advantage of your best possible rate (which are at a current historical low), while enjoying long-term security.\n        \n        If you value flexibility, a shorter-term mortgage will often allow you to take advantage of lower rates to save money, while being less of a term commitment.\n        \n        At True North Mortgage, our friendly, expert brokers really know mortgages and can quickly lay out the pros and cons of different term lengths based on your current financial situation. They'll help you discuss the options for your short and long-term goals and find the right term and lender to match your needs."},{question:"What is a fixed-rate mortgage?",answer:"A fixed-rate mortgage is a type of mortgage where the interest rate is set for a pre-determined term, usually between 6 months to 10 years. A fixed-rate mortgage offers the security of knowing what you will be paying for the term selected.\n        \n        Read More: [How Government Bond Yields Relate To Mortgage Rates](INSERT LINK)"},{question:"What is a variable-rate mortgage?",answer:"A variable-rate mortgage is a type of mortgage where the interest rate is tied to the prime lending rate and will increase or decrease along with it.\n        \n        If prime goes up, so does your payment \u2014 or if your payment is static, then more of your payment will go towards interest costs and less down on the principal. If prime goes down, your payment will also go down, or more will be put towards the principal and less for interest."},{question:"Can you have more than one high ratio mortgage?",answer:"A high ratio mortgage is one where your down payment at the time of purchase is less than 20%. In all such cases, the mortgage is insured by CMHC, Sagen, or Canada Guaranty.\n        \n        As long as you plan to live in the second property, then you can have a second home with a high ratio mortgage. If the property you are buying is intended as a rental, then you MUST put down at least 20%.\n        \n        Here are a couple of possible scenarios:\n        1) You buy a second home, cottage, condo, or whatever for your own use. It is not a rental property.\n        2) You decide to buy a new home and convert the home you are now living in into a rental property. Your new home can have a down payment of less than 20%."},{question:"Is a 25-year amortization better than a 30-year amortization?",answer:'The answer depends on your situation. If you can totally afford a 25-year amortization, then it would be considered "better," as you would pay off your mortgage in less time and pay much less interest over time.\n        \n        But maybe you cannot qualify for a mortgage with a 25-year amortization. In that case, a 30-year amortization is essential. In fact, a couple of lenders will even offer a 35-year amortization if necessary.\n        \n        If you are going to have a 30-year amortization, you MUST have at least 20% equity in your property.'},{question:"If I buy a plot of land, will I qualify for a mortgage?",answer:"It's hard to get mortgage financing on a piece of unserviced land. At best, you are probably looking at needing at least a 50% down payment.\n        \n        And if you are looking for A-lender rates, this is probably going to get done only in the branch networks, and not with your mortgage broker. You might want to knock on the door of your favorite credit union."},{question:"Will I qualify for a mortgage with 20% down payment after I pay off my consumer proposal?",answer:"A mortgage to purchase a home may be doable once you start to generate scores from your new credit cards. There are a lot of factors, and location is HUGE because you will be talking with B-lenders and they are very picky where they lend.\n        \n        They like urban, well-populated areas. Rural and well and septic are very hard. You will certainly need a 20% DP and maybe as much as 35% depending on when you do this, and where you buy and your employment and income, etc."},{question:"Will my mortgage be approved if I am on probation at work?",answer:"It really depends on your overall profile. If the new job is in the same industry you have been in for years and if it is for more money, you have a good chance of being approved. And if you are in a high-demand industry like I.T., healthcare, education, that helps too. Multiple recent job changes or a new industry is more challenging. Do please ask us BEFORE you firm up an offer to purchase."},{question:"Can we use an old appraisal report for our mortgage refinance?",answer:"Appraisals have to be very recent and not stale-dated and in rising markets, this is also in your best interests as your property has gone up markedly in value since the last time one was done.\n        \n        And when talking about private mortgages or B-lender mortgages, the lower the appraised value, the higher the potential rate. And if the appraisal came in too low, it might take some lenders out of their comfort zone. So a good, fresh appraisal report is essential to a good mortgage result."},{question:"Should I choose a fixed-rate or variable-rate mortgage?",answer:"For many years, those who chose a variable-rate mortgage have fared better than those who chose a fixed rate. Interest rates fell year after year, and the VRM acolytes saved lots of money compared to their friends.\n        \n        And today the difference between the two rates is still quite compelling. BUT it would appear rates have far more room to increase in coming years than any other time in recent memory. And for many people, a fixed rate is certain, whereas the VRM is a step into the unknown.\n        \n        So the answer is... it depends. Talk first to your trusted advisers. See what makes sense for YOU."},{question:"Do mortgage lenders check both credit report scores?",answer:"There are two credit reporting agencies in Canada Equifax and TransUnion. Mortgage brokers access a copy of your Equifax report and submit it with your application to lenders. In some situations, some lenders will also pull a copy of your TransUnion report. And in the branches, some lenders will go first to TransUnion.\n        \n        The bottom line for consumers is that it is wise to keep both reports healthy and with no errors."},{question:"What should I do to win in a multi-offer situation?",answer:"It often takes a few miserable outings before one succeeds. My sense is to win, one must make an aggressive offer, almost outside one's comfort zone, and understand that over market value might be the end result but if you don't do it, the winner will, and regardless, a new market value is established.\n        \n        You need to accommodate the seller as much as possible when it comes to the closing date, and do bring a husky deposit to the party. At least 5% of the purchase price is good.\n        \n        Try to get a home inspection done at your own expense if time and access permit, prior to making your offer.\n        \n        And if your real estate agent (even your mortgage agent too) makes a nice presentation about you to the sellers, this can also help. Video presentations can be very effective."},{question:"What is an assignment of rents?",answer:"This is part of your mortgage loan agreement, which entitles the lender to any income (from leases, rents, etc.) derived from the property once the owner defaults on the loan.\n        \n        So it is a big deal only if you stop making mortgage payments and is reasonable for the lender to require. It is a fairly standard clause on all private and B-mortgages."},{question:"What if the appraisal comes in low?",answer:'We are often asked what will happen if the appraisal comes in lower. Will the home buyer still be able to finance it?\n        \n        We always hope the appraisal will come in at the agreed price. But often in a super heated market, the buyer may have "overbid" in order to win the property.\n        \n        The lender would still lend the agreed percentage of the purchase price, or the appraised value, whichever is less.\n        \n        If that leaves a shortfall, you need to have access to additional money. If not, you may need to tap into the "Bank of Mom and Dad."'},{question:"Is the condo status certificate important for mortgage financing?",answer:'Our client wrote me and said, "I am intending to put in an offer on this unit. I had a lawyer review the status certificate. The status certificate package did not include the most recent audited financials. Will this impact on my ability to get financing? The lawyer indicated I should bring this to your attention."\n        \n        I answered, "I believe that if there are no such financials by the time of closing, that this could jeopardize your purchase.\n        \n        Our team had one like this not long ago. The lawyer never mentioned the missing financials, and when it was going through final review, just before closing, the lender wanted it (rightfully so). We managed to get the financials in time so it closed but it was dicey.\n        \n        The seller\'s realtor can perhaps find out when the financials will be available, and you could set a closing date accordingly for a few weeks after that IF you feel confident their answer will turn out to be true."\n        \n        The review of the status certificate is typically a solicitor condition, not a broker condition. The solicitor reports back to the lender as to whether or not there are issues.\n        \n        The status certificate review is a critical and important part of the condo purchase process.'},{question:"What are the advantages and disadvantages of bi-weekly mortgage payments?",answer:"Many borrowers choose bi-weekly perhaps because they read somewhere that is the best repayment strategy \u2014 fully believing this will pay the whole she-bang off faster and with much less interest over time.\n        \n        But this is not accurate.\n        \n        Here is where I bust the bi-weekly myth wide open. Bi-weekly payments (and weekly payments) may make no difference to the long run of your mortgage. What?! No difference?!\n        \n        BI-WEEKLY PAYMENTS DO NOT SHORTEN THE AMORTIZATION PERIOD\n        BI-WEEKLY PAYMENTS DO NOT REDUCE THE AMOUNT OF INTEREST\n        BI-WEEKLY PAYMENTS DO NOT INCREASE THE AMOUNT OF PRINCIPAL BEING REPAID\n        \n        They serve as a convenience, not a money-saving tool. Good to know, right?!\n        \n        Let me explain\u2026\n        \n        To get the sizzle in your bi-weekly payment, you have to request accelerated bi-weekly payments. Accelerated means you divide the normal monthly payment by two and pay that every two weeks.\n        \n        Lenders typically offer either bi-weekly payments or accelerated bi-weekly payments. Accelerated bi-weekly payments shorten the amortization period, reduce the amount of interest paid over time, and even pay back principal faster.\n        \n        They are both a convenience AND a money saver. So basically, accelerated bi-weekly payments are your budgetary BFF.\n        \n        So if you just care about matching mortgage payments to your bi-weekly paycheck, go ahead and request bi-weekly payments.\n        \n        BUT if you want to get ahead of the curve too, then you should ask for accelerated bi-weekly payments."},{question:"What if my GDSR and TDSR are a few percent over the limit?",answer:"Is it possible that I could get a pre-approval and eventually a mortgage in spite of this?\n        \n        Regarding securing a mortgage with debt service ratios a bit high yes, there are some ways we can make that work depends on several factors including:\n        \n        - Is this a high-ratio mortgage (less than 20% down payment or not)? If it is a high-ratio, then no, we are in tough.\n        - But if you have more than 20% down payment, we can work with credit unions and other alternative lenders who take a different approach toward underwriting a mortgage."},{question:"Will my maternity leave hurt our mortgage approval?",answer:"Not usually a problem. If you can produce a letter from your employer providing a return to work date with your position and expected compensation at that time, then it is as if you are still working. This is just as true for dads taking paternity leave."},{question:"Can I get a mortgage to pay my CRA debt?",answer:"Chances are your bank will say no, you cannot. However, we have dozens of lenders who will readily pay this debt with mortgage financing. It might be a brand new first mortgage or maybe a temporary private second mortgage. No problem!"},{question:"What are your fees when you refinance a mortgage?",answer:"Fees associated with a mortgage refinance vary considerably, depending on your unique circumstances.\n        \n        - Mortgage Prepayment Penalty: Unless your current mortgage is fully open or is exactly at the renewal date, your lender will charge you a prepayment penalty as you leave.\n        - Legal fees and disbursements: All mortgage refinances require the use of real estate lawyers. If your new mortgage is with a private lender, you will be expected to pay for your own lawyer as well as the lender's lawyer.\n        - Lender and brokerage fees: If you are refinancing with an A-lender, there should be no brokerage or lender fees charged. But if your new mortgage is with an alternative lender, you will be charged such fees. [Learn more](https://askross.ca/what-does-a-private-mortgage-cost/)\n        - Appraisal costs: An appraisal costs from a few hundred dollars to well over $1,000. The cost depends on location, value, and urgency a rush job will cost more."},{question:"How much does a mortgage broker cost?",answer:"There should be no cost if your mortgage is with a bank or some other A-lender. Brokerage fees are typically charged on private mortgages and B-lender mortgages. The amount depends on the size of the loan and the complexity of the client's situation. We are always clear and upfront about any such costs no surprises!"},{question:"Why is our high-ratio mortgage advance less than expected?",answer:"The likely primary reason is that you need to pay 8% PST on the mortgage insurance premium.\n        \n        For example, with a $607,000 mortgage, the insurance premium may be $18,817.\n        \n        The premium is added onto your mortgage amount, which becomes $625,817.\n        \n        However, there is PST charged on the insurance, which is $1,505.36.\n        \n        Likely, they deducted it from the advance. Any other variance might be explained by the interest adjustment date."},{question:"When will I need a bridge mortgage?",answer:'There are several scenarios where you might need a bridge mortgage, but yes, downsizing is a classic. If the sale of your current home is firmed up, this is a relatively easy transaction for your bank. But if you have not yet sold your home, you may need a private mortgage arranged by your mortgage broker.\n        \n        Suppose you are buying a new home, but the one you are in will not sell before your closing date. You get approved for a regular mortgage for the property you are buying, PLUS another temporary mortgage to cover your down payment and closing costs until your current home sells. The temporary mortgage is the bridge mortgage.\n        \n        It essentially helps you "bridge" the gap between the time your current home is sold and your new home is being purchased. This is why the solution is called a bridge mortgage. At Ross Taylor Mortgages, we will make all the arrangements for you.'},{question:"How do I find a cheap real estate lawyer?",answer:"Competent, capable, and service-oriented trump cheapest cost. I don't ask the lawyers we deal with to discount their services, but I do expect a seamless client experience. Why would you cheap out on such a majorly important service for the largest financial transaction you have ever done?"},{question:"Can I change my job now that my mortgage has been approved?",answer:"This is definitely not recommended. If you resign from your job prior to your purchase completing, then your mortgage approval would be at serious risk. Mortgage lenders can do a verbal confirmation of employment (by telephone) up to and including the funding date. If you have resigned, even if you are still there on that date, your employer would probably share this information with the lender and that would be that. Please tread very carefully."},{question:"Prequalified vs. Preapproved? What's the difference?",answer:"With most lenders, these things mean the same thing based on a review of your information and documentation, the lender is comfortable telling you your maximum borrowing power. It is not an iron-clad approval for when you actually buy a property. Suppose your circumstances change or the property has serious structural issues you may yet not be approved after you agree to a purchase."},{question:"Why does my lender not remit my property taxes to the municipality?",answer:"Sometimes clients are confused that the tax statement sent by their township does not reflect all the payments they have already made directly to their mortgage lender. Regarding your property taxes, when a lender remits taxes on your behalf they do so according to their own internal schedule and processes. And that would not necessarily be the same as the schedule you would follow if remitting yourself. If you have recently changed mortgage lenders or just completed a home purchase, your real estate lawyer is the first person I would turn to here when trying to find out the status of your property tax account. The previous lender should have provided an accounting of their tax remittance account to her at the time of payout. That can be compared to the city billings to figure out where you are actually at."},{question:"How quickly will our mortgage close?",answer:"Our client asked this question after she gave us the last document still outstanding as requested by her mortgage lender. The fact is we are likely looking at two more weeks from that date. This was a refinance and here is what remained to be done: Even at this late stage, the lender has to sign off on all your documents; then declare the file is complete. Then the lender and Charles send packages to your lawyer. Then your lawyer requests a payout statement from RBC (and we wait for that they control how fast they give it.) Then your lawyer and you coordinate signing meeting. In general for refinances, I tell our clients we allow five to six weeks from beginning to end. If a particular lender is slow, I will tell our clients and we will expect it to take longer. Don/t get me wrong, we know how to close rush deals if we have to in case of emergency. Last year we closed a $3 million purchase only one week after we received the file! But that was a special case and \u201call hands on deck\u201d. We also counsel clients to avoid closing dates at the very end of the month or the very beginning of the month, if at all possible. Those dates are when lenders and lawyers are busiest."},{question:"I completed a consumer proposal two years ago, would I be considered for a mortgage?",answer:"Yes you have a shot at mortgage consideration, but it ultimately depends on many factors. Is the CP still showing on your credit? Have you reestablished new credit? Are you thinking of buying or refinancing? How large a down payment do you have? Etc."},{question:"What are your typical rates and LTV for a private mortgage?",answer:"Rates are all over the place depending on if you are borrowing or lending. Location matters. Loan to value matters. Property type matters and so does whether or not we are talking about a first or a second mortgage. Please call me at my direct number 416-989-1050 and I will be happy to spend a few minutes with you and better answer your question. You can also check out our three part series on private mortgages here."},{question:"What happens if the appraisal value is lower than my purchase price?",answer:"Buyers do need to have a financial cushion so that if the property appraises light they can make up the difference. That is the challenge I see here. If you have no additional savings or investments, you could have a serious problem and in danger of not completing your purchase. Example: final price $1.3 million. Buyer expecting to put down 20% = $260,000. But appraised price is $1.2 million. Buyer must put up $340,000 now."},{question:"Are there any alternatives to be able to get a loan for the down payment and closing costs?",answer:"I have to admit it is tough if you do not have any funds to put towards the purchase. There is something called a Flex Down mortgage but you need to come up with the financing yourself could be a Personal Line of Credit perhaps. Some municipalities will offer DP assistance. I did a couple in Orangeville a few years ago. Maybe one near you might offer the same. I would go to city hall and ask them if they have a down payment assistance program or if they know of one in a nearby municipality."},{question:"What is the best way to beat the mortgage stress test these days?",answer:"The lower the stress test rate, the more mortgage you qualify for. If you take a variable rate mortgage, your stress test rate is \u201conly\u201d 5.25%. But if you take a fixed rate mortgage, your stress test rate will be around 6.5% (depending on the actual fixed rate you are being given) We work with credit unions and other lenders who have mortgage products that qualify you at your actual mortgage contract rate so if the fixed rate is 4.44%, that is your stress test rate! This is a huge benefit."},{question:"Why does my mortgage lender take out too much for property taxes?",answer:"We hear this complaint in the months following a purchase in situations where the homeowner has to pay property taxes through the mortgage lender. The lender takes an amount for the mortgage and also an amount for property taxes from the borrower/s bank account on the agreed payment schedule. The reason its more than you would expect is that all lenders like to seed the tax account so that there is always extra in there no matter when the city comes along and collects it. Generally by the second year things get sorted out and the amounts being withdrawn each payment adds up to the actual annual property taxes."},{question:"Can I pay my property taxes directly to the municipality?",answer:"Absolutely yes you can. Many first time buyers find themselves in an arrangement where there is a tax payment withdrawn from their bank account at the same time as their mortgage payment. But for various reasons, they would rather manage the payments themselves. Personally, I set up an equal monthly amount to be deducted from my bank account by way of Bill Payment. Others contact their municipality and enter into a payment plan directly with them. Whatever approach you wish to take, you will need to apprise your current mortgage lender of any changes."},{question:"What is the cost of a mortgage pre-approval?",answer:"There is no cost for the pre-approval. When you consummate the purchase of your home, you will have normal closing costs. They are outlined in this article https://askross.ca/top-10-things-your-home-buying-budget-needs-to-include-in-addition-to-the-purchase-price/ When we receive an approval, the lender will indicate whether or not they require an appraisal done on the property. The cost varies, especially by location. In Toronto, properties under a million should cost less than $400. We typically share the cost with our clients as a show of goodwill. As to other specific costs arising from your mortgage that is mostly between you and your real estate lawyer who will charge you a fee to register the mortgage, purchase title insurance, accept monies from the lender and various other tasks. All reputable lawyers have a well-defined cost for these services. As brokers, and for the A-lenders we represent, there are no other incremental expenses."},{question:"With 20% down payment, how much will our closing costs be?",answer:"Assuming you are a first-time buyer in Ontario, and the purchase price is say $800,000, closing costs are typically: 1) Legal fees, disbursements and title insurance $2,500 to $3,000 2) Land Transfer Tax LTT (in Toronto) $16,475 LTT outside Toronto is only $8,475 3) Interest Rate Adjustment $0 to $3,000 (depends on lender and your closing date) 4) Moving Expenses up to you $1,000 and upwards Those are the main costs required to close the purchase of a home with no CMHC insurance. If the DP is less than 20% you also have to pay the 8% PST on the insurance premium (roughly $1,500) If you choose to buy from a builder (or assignment of a pre-construction property) there would be more closing costs for sure."},{question:"Should we be worried our appraisal value did not exceed the purchase price?",answer:"This is not a silly question. In the summer of 2022 it is not uncommon for appraisals to come in lower than the agreed purchase price. This can play havoc on buyers finances. Our client asked \u201cGiven that the appraisal came pretty close to the purchasing value, should we be worried about the bank requesting a second appraisal closer to the closing date? How long is this appraisal good for?\u201d"}],b=a(4048),v=a(7661),k=a(184),I=function(){var e=(0,o.useState)(""),t=(0,i.Z)(e,2),a=t[0],r=t[1],n=w.filter((function(e){return e.question.toLowerCase().includes(a.toLowerCase())}));return(0,k.jsxs)(s.k,{direction:["column","row"],justify:"space-between",children:[(0,k.jsxs)(l.xu,{flex:"3",p:4,minHeight:"80vh",children:[(0,k.jsx)(h.X,{children:"FAQ"}),(0,k.jsx)(u.I,{mt:4,mb:4,placeholder:"Search...",onChange:function(e){r(e.target.value)}}),(0,k.jsx)(d.U,{mt:4,allowToggle:!0,children:(0,k.jsx)(y.g,{spacing:4,align:"stretch",children:n.map((function(e,t){return(0,k.jsxs)(c.Q,{children:[(0,k.jsx)("h2",{children:(0,k.jsxs)(m.K,{children:[(0,k.jsx)(l.xu,{flex:"1",textAlign:"left",children:e.question}),(0,k.jsx)(g.X,{})]})}),(0,k.jsx)(p.H,{pb:4,children:(0,k.jsx)(f.x,{children:e.answer})})]},t)}))})})]}),(0,k.jsx)(l.xu,{flex:"1",position:"sticky",top:"0",height:"fit-content",children:(0,k.jsx)(b.Z,{})})]})},T=a(375),x=a(8675),q=a(6819),A=a(1087),S=(0,q.E)(y.g),R=function(){return(0,k.jsxs)(S,{textAlign:"center",pt:"40vh",initial:{x:-300,opacity:0},animate:{x:0,opacity:1},transition:{type:"spring",stiffness:50},children:[(0,k.jsx)(h.X,{as:"h1",size:"2xl",color:"white",textTransform:"uppercase",fontSize:"5vw",mt:"-10rem",children:"FAQ"}),(0,k.jsx)(x.i,{w:"5%",borderColor:"custom.text",mt:"30px",mb:"30px"}),(0,k.jsx)(v.Z,{as:A.rU,to:"/sign-in",variant:"outline",size:"sm",children:"Apply Now"})]})},C=a(5531),N=function(){return(0,k.jsxs)(k.Fragment,{children:[(0,k.jsxs)(r.q,{children:[(0,k.jsx)("meta",{name:"description",content:"Find answers to common mortgage-related FAQs."}),(0,k.jsx)("meta",{name:"keywords",content:"how much can I afford to pay for a home, home inspection, minimum down payment, home loan insurance, conventional mortgage, bankruptcy affecting mortgage qualification, child support affecting mortgage qualification, using gift funds to get a mortgage, pre-approved mortgage, renewing a mortgage, paying off your mortgage faster, RRSP, costs associated with buying a home, length of mortgage terms, monthly costs of owning a home, fixed-rate mortgage, variable-rate mortgage, high ratio mortgage, 25-year amortization, 30-year amortization, consumer proposal, probation, old appraisal report, credit score, multi-offer, assignment of rents, low appraisal, condo status certificate, bi-weekly mortgage payments, GDSR, TDSR, maternity leave affecting mortgage approval, CRA debt, refinance fees, cost of a mortgage agent, bridge a mortgage, cheap real estate lawyer, job change post mortgage approval, prequalified vs. preapproved, property taxes, how quickly will our mortgage close, consumer proposal, private mortgage, LTV, closing costs, mortgage stress test, mortgage lender, pre-approval, 20% down payment, appraisal value"}),(0,k.jsx)("meta",{name:"robots",content:"index, follow"})]}),(0,k.jsx)(n.Z,{}),(0,k.jsx)(l.xu,{bgImage:"url(".concat(C,")"),bgSize:"cover",bgPos:"center",m:"2rem",h:"100vh",children:(0,k.jsx)(R,{})}),(0,k.jsx)(l.xu,{pb:"5em",w:{base:"100%",sm:"100%",md:"80%"},mx:{base:"0",sm:"0",md:"auto"},bgColor:"white",mt:"-25em",p:"2em",borderRadius:"md",boxShadow:"0 0 10px rgba(0,0,0,0.2)",mb:"5em",children:(0,k.jsx)(y.g,{pb:"5",children:(0,k.jsx)(I,{})})}),(0,k.jsx)(T.Z,{})]})}}}]);
//# sourceMappingURL=923.515282d3.chunk.js.map